welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
here there'll be some people trickling
in we've got quite a few folks RSVP'd
for today's talk and I can understand
why so hello everyone welcome to the
stoah the stoah is a digital campfire
where we cohere in dialogue about what
matters most at the knife's edge of this
moment I'm Raven a host here at the
stoah this evening we are joined by
Rachel haywire a philosopher writer
artist designer futurist and
entrepreneur rachel has written several
works her most recent publication the
new art write makes the argument for a
new transgressive aesthetic movement in
this talk rachel will be addressing the
questions how do we explore creativity
and transgression during a pandemic can
we divorce aesthetics from politics what
role will art music and literature play
during this time
Rachel will have the floor for about 20
minutes and then we will open it up to
questions from the audience and with
that I bring you
Rachel haywire hi everybody I'm sticking
my INGOs uh how is this everybody good
angle alright so you guys are here to
talk about creativity and
self-expression with me we're having a
giant discussion about expressing
ourselves during appends I'm like a time
that is considered to be maybe not the
end of history but I stopped in history
a change of the guards a change of
forces perhaps a a new start and a new
beginning or maybe there's some people
just new destruction um but regardless
of what this is about we are in the
midst of pandemic now and we're gonna
need to start getting creative in a way
that we previously didn't need to and
this is going to take a new type of
transgression that is robust it's going
to take a type of transgression
isn't showy but that isn't so concerned
about being private a transgression that
knows where it is and how it is
transgressing and what precisely it is
trans Garcia a direct movement an
aesthetic movement a lot of people will
put down movements for their popular
sentiments or have populist grievances
about how movements are for the elite
definitions of movement might vary when
when I think of an aesthetic movement I
think of aesthetics transforming
creating reforming and unifying and also
separating a new movement moves in
various directions that are not known to
the previous era the previous decade I'm
turning Yan cycle whatever one may call
it um and when we get to transgression
in a pandemic era we're gonna need to
ask ourselves a few questions on one are
we really going to do with these these
tribalists left-right blue red anti Pro
is any of this meaningful or do we just
need to have an art right so we just
need to have a beard left do we just
need to have a fun Center do we just
need to go away from the mean political
zeitgeist rate which which isn't serving
us right now and make it into an
aesthetic creation of our primal core um
and our internal visions when Peter was
giving this talk about unleashing that
inner demon before I was thinking about
the powerful metaphor of the lesioning
the forces the dark forces within
yourself in a way where you're creating
something that could be beautiful that
could be suffering and pain but high
mighty kingdoms kingdoms in the sky
Imperium of minds and and that's when I
came I'm like okay what are you going to
do to create an Imperium of the minds
right
what are you gonna do to have a kingdom
of the minds and which you are deciding
how the aesthetics flow you are
directing the film you are doing the
photo shoot you are recording the track
where you know that the Imperium of the
mind is being explored in a way that
personally makes you feel you know that
moment is there it's a flash it's a
flash that you know and when you feel
that bless you right there you are on
you are on it I know a lot of people
they they want to get to that moment and
they don't always have the best methods
of doing that I mean some people they'll
do a bunch of drugs other people will
will go on a expensive vacations and get
in bad relationships um but you know
when we're talking about what would
Peter referred to earlier as the knife's
edge you're gonna encounter a lot of
volatility and you're gonna have to know
like how to scale that in a positive way
and when to get rid of the bad parts
about what's Lydia Bitzer are really
prominent right now how can you stay on
the knife's edge and create how can you
still the name says we without like
having the the darker energy of
transgression and its destructive forces
consume you how does one pull that off
um as a stable sand a being that is
looking to express themselves right um I
think that's an important thing to look
at how do you channel that demon inside
of you do you about it get the best of
your other people or do you focus it you
have a precise focus like a precise
movement the aesthetic move man it needs
to be first ie some if you think about
the Italian futurist French situation is
the Dada is some the beatniks the mods
various subcultures goth Punk in bitter
very of movements like French literature
and like German Expressionism and like
the Italian Renaissance new eras I'm
decades come in
the Jews that culture share you know I'm
like released into the curtains like
they sin and out in in it but not of it
right where we're in it but not of it
but now we are creating a new it that we
are becoming into you that's what we're
doing we're building aesthetic movement
some other Metis tribes are doing it now
are we doing one universally maybe maybe
not do we need to what what if we don't
need to have a universal movement what
what if it's cool that we have millions
of factions and that will scale
creativity their most efficiently to so
to speak right um and and what defines a
movement what defines a movement is that
the clothing that you wear is it the
language just that you speak in the
secret codes that you use the status
hierarchies that you assign a long
people who you kick out this who you
kick out to find a movement I resumed
have been stronger with or without
certain certain like designated you know
people to be the out the end opinion in
iron in do we need an in-group and
out-group to create do we need to have
that elitism as a basis for creation and
outside of PC liberal norm right Chi can
we transgress that without becoming the
villain so to speak Jim can we see
things for how they are with El backing
down Sharon can we see things for how
they are without backing down defining
movements you can't back down you have
to be forceful in a way that people
interact with aesthetically um this is
why I like so much of the dissident
Bryant movement has failed is because
their aesthetics they don't really
appeal to any group of people outside of
their you know little little community
and they they've got like their their
path is right like that's too you know
the guy I found um you know just like
the little folk things that would be
cute for definitely definitely not
enough
and just like the volatility that a lot
of people have in that community is
really bad and you know like when we're
talking about gonna art right or like a
beard braid or like a new left or like
an alternative Center when when we come
up with these new political terms and
new for the phrases to describe like
these metaphysical political Birds
tribal connections within maybe
political archetypes um so to speak like
you're building a political universe
right um artistically um can you do that
can can you build a political universe
artistically this is their art in
politics or should it be divorced from
politics entirely is it okay to
political art if somebody makes
political art should they be shunned for
succumbing to those urges if somebody
makes for the arts should they be
assigned a certain status because they
are cause artists because they make
their art with different causes should
they get more prominence or or should we
work to counter that with our that is
breathtaking but does not so within
their frame I hear a lot of people they
say I don't like how the art world has
all of these social justice rules and PC
was shining and I hear a lot of people
complaining about it but I'm not sure
that many people are doing anything
about it sometimes I feel like they just
want to complain I'd say like make your
own shows produce your own events you
know you can do that now this is a pen
diamond you have more opportunities like
I used to when I was young and like even
more crazy yeah I used to think that
there is gonna be an apocalypse and that
me and all my friends would survive and
we'd be like the first apocalypse if you
have that you know that it's fun you
know you can be like very imaginative
now you can be very imaginative and I'm
you don't want to hold your minds back
when you're getting to that creative
fine um like let yourself go
yourself feel that being unleashed you
can feel it being unleashed when you
explore you you have uncertainty right
now you don't know what is gonna happen
tomorrow you know pretty much but I mean
anything could be announced on the news
that could change everything and there's
a lot of scares there are a lot of
things announced in the news that don't
change anything at all so can you use
that uncertainty in a way that makes you
more expressive or do you feel trapped
by it and if you feel trapped by it what
are you going to do with the uncertainty
how can you make them stir in your bitch
I get how can you make and certainty a
toy that you're gonna play with what are
you gonna do when you haven't standing
in front of you how are you gonna
channel that moment in a way that works
for you and I wanted to address on like
people like them talking about how they
feel like they can't see certain things
like in the art pearls and the whole
reason that art exists at least like
from a certain point is to see things
that you can't say verbally um that you
can't say and like regular conversation
you express them through aesthetic Birds
the higher pieces whether it's art or
music or literature you express them in
a way that you connect with people that
you're sharing specific mythologies and
symbols with you have an entirely new
universe when you're creating in this
way we are all alice is designing our
own Wonderland
we all have bad ability I'm rubberdam
tumbles in ease the reality is what you
can get away with now I don't agree with
that I actually believe in an objective
reality but it's fun to explore that
possibility you know and just think of
what what if reality didn't really exist
what if reality was just some bounce
track like
could you do that like everything is
crashing down everything becomes more
and more like the onion right and now
we're rebuilding from the satirical
ashes of a pandemic society like this is
literally what we're doing right now
we're rebuilding from the literal ashes
a pandemic Society and the experts have
no idea what's going on but did they
ever and if they didn't which I'm
starting to think they did not then
doesn't that mean we have a lot more
power than we previously thought if
we're thinking of the people that are in
our way have no idea how to handle
something at this scale it shows us that
maybe a lot of the doors that we thought
were closed actually are open for us
because they're all just kind of
signaling you know they're all just kind
of signaling from I mean I think that
leaves a lot open so I don't know how
many of you are artists or musicians or
writers or just creative people but I
know that a lot of people think they
cannot focus on that aspect of
themselves because it will make them too
unrestrained I mean and as someone who's
gone through it on like you just you
find that line like you find the knife I
just thought you can tolerate you finds
it where you have the power the knife
and you know when it's too much like
when you're scaling the extreme fringe
like you know when it's too far we're
gonna need you better bring in yourself
back in you know like go as far as you
want would be able to rein yourself back
in um and the aesthetic movements that
are happening right now like if you
really think about it it doesn't seem
like they're there are that many um a
lot of people mentioned Burning Man is
kind of like a mix we've got the
subcultures and and before that there
was like steampunk right I forgot but
there hasn't really been anything
that's really been like a movement like
this subculture like that I mean there's
been like different internet groups and
different digital tribes but there
hasn't really been like a subculture
with that kind of magnitude maybe we've
just outgrown it um and my society not
maybe we've just outgrown subculture
mode now where we're all monolithic um
but it feels like now is a good time to
explore different subcultures that we
hadn't really focused on before maybe so
cultures that would be more viable now
because of people learning for the first
time what's actually going on you know I
mean people have become more a week in a
way where you can do things that you
couldn't before and they're gonna be
looking to you for advice um so it's
just like a good time to think about
what you're capable of right now um and
anybody can build an aesthetic movement
and get people to join them you focus on
style your focus on your personal
desires and how you can build them in
the external world like whether it's
through creating a piece of art that has
a vision that you had display it on it
now I'm just showing a people that
creative primal part of you and
translating it translating it into the
universe so people can pick up on the
connections that you have brought them
on there is a deep ecologist element in
art aesthetics are are deeply occult
they're hidden they're not on the
surface the surface is where everything
is literal that's why people get in
trouble for saying things that they
would have get in trouble for making art
of because art isn't on the surface it's
a cult hidden and I would also say that
it is on a different metaphysical kind
of thing
I'm in terms of like having visions come
to you and just having snaps then it's
permission you know like just like we
feel something and you're like that's
what I've been looking for you know I
just comes to you just start writing
like crazy for example you know like
that was urges that just make you go to
where you've been waiting to go for so
long and you're finally there like
that's the kind of thing to be
channeling um and some you know there
are some concerns like I don't want to
hurt anybody I'm pretty you know extreme
you might be thinking it's yours live
right now I don't want to hurt anyone
that's what you have to learn so what
you have to learn it's the the process
you know I'm you have that demonic you
know inspiration I mean even if it's
positive and you've learned to channel
it and you've learned to make it work
for you in the most optimal way you
still have to know like them wants to
kick back with it and also like when to
not let your ego be involved at all when
to just step away see things for how
they are and don't involve yourself at
all and that there are so many modes to
this type of interaction I I think you
can learn from a lot of people that you
might not think that you can you know
I'm people that that seemed to be a
repetitive and mundane be they might be
really good at doing things that you're
not good at and
trying to view best judgmental of people
that I'm previously called boring you
know or like I'm exciting not passionate
enough or let's be dramatic not cool
enough like I'm so cool there's
something right um but I I try to just
look at everybody further individual
selves you know like what is somebody
expressing something aesthetically what
is somebody's aesthetic you can learn a
lot about people from their aesthetic
but they put out in the world with the
way that they dress the way they speak
the way they present themselves with the
things they're into the things they
surround themselves with the art that
they produce the music that release the
ways that they communicate you can kind
of feel their aesthetic and you can be
like okay that's lose your aesthetic and
you might know it before I might be
familiar to you or you might be learning
about a new aesthetic entirely
I'm sorry so the thing in this agreement
is essentially you're eating in a way
that people will want to join in you're
creating something and people want to
join you you we're gonna project that
you tell a few people about it tell a
few people don't suddenly got like a
hundred people are again ever had to
actually vote miss thetic movements and
I encourage everybody to do so don't
don't worry about sacred cows don't
worry about impressing people never do
it so they get in with some clip that
you feel is beneath you that's just like
really really doing any work like if you
have to get in with the cookie if
there's anything you do not do it
whatever the thing is finds people that
you relate to I have a tweet where I
talk about this um you can follow me on
Twitter at beyond the center and I have
a treat just find people you can relate
to you find people who you work well
with find people that understand your
visions don't worry about who's in the
center of power but me others like you
that you connect
and a lot of people they they get um
really driven by these these power games
but you need to learn without a doubt
but if you're all optics and no action
or all app tips and I'm aesthetic I'm
gonna call you about like like I just
called Curtis carbon and then she
smelled bad and I got like hundreds of
people telling me like how dare you even
so well he houses new sense of
aesthetics you know that's just not his
thing but we need aesthetics oh my god I
had like 20 people to fill me with that
I think he needs to do something about
the hair it seems like there's this
theme going and what you're saying I was
like its pre-existing like you mentioned
that as a movement that we were
inherited we're kind of inside of right
now and it's calcified right so you have
like the social justice kind of post
modernist side which has really claimed
art I mean in a really serious way they
have like staked their territory around
art and all art as political and it's
interesting how that approach to art is
very overt which is almost the opposite
of what you're talking about in terms of
prints ggressive art or art as
transgressive action or communication it
is not so obvious what it means to be
and it's up to the the experience
between the art and the end experience
of the artist and the person
experiencing the art to discover in that
space between what the implications of
that interaction is and it seems that
this idea of transgressive is both kind
of bringing back to this quality of art
that breaks through categories which I
see also in other elements of your work
you're taking like the art right is like
taking art which is like a leftist
product and moving it into the right
which is like appreciation of hierarchy
and tradition and like and mashing them
together beyond the center how can you
be a be beyond a center so I see this
like pattern
your work of trying to remix all of the
categorical assumptions that we have and
that's being kind of the origin of
rebirth of this new aesthetic movement
do you see do you have anything yeah I
like the way they put that I feel like
that's the resurrection anymore you
could even say the insurrection and it's
like an aesthetic it's direction of the
Spirit you know like it's a feeling you
just you know it it's like when you've
reached the Empire - just eat and when
you you have that force you can do
whatever you want with it but you do
have to be careful sometimes um and it's
not even productive to even discuss the
people who are censoring and banning
things because it's just why are we not
building better things like why are they
even a topic like I do not want to talk
about people that are holding us back
with these codes is the fault of
whatever they're they're doing there
yeah what why should we even have to
communicate at that level of where where
everybody's hiding I mean like were
literally wearing masks right now it
makes sense but if you think about how
everybody was hiding before and all the
repression and the it's just it's not a
good environment to be and
self-expression and art and it's some it
doesn't hurt anybody you know so you
can't um be yeah yeah art is a way to
almost like Anna Strauss II and sense to
transgress the limits of like heterodox
thinking because you display it in a way
that isn't immediately understandable to
people but the people who get it they
really get it and it draws them in
totally yeah so I
get two more questions I saw that Peter
mentioned he had a question so if you
would like to unmute yourself Peter
invite anybody else to put that question
to the test process one beer kind of
mixes up the game one energy and so the
question relates to insanity sacrifice
and community because artists you know
they're on the brink of insanity if they
follow the dame on energy exactly where
places no else wants to go
and I'm wondering will came alive to me
when you were talking rachel is that is
sacrificing your sanity or or should I
say relying on others for your sanity
and sacrificing it is that an act of
love why me think about that
it can mean I think that yeah it's
directed in
away where
oh yeah I think if it's directed yes
what do you mean by directed I'm curious
well this conception of sanity changes
all the time so if you can have like a
really productive insanity you know like
an optimal schizophrenia there's
something like that I was reading them
the glands of course I'm talking about
optimal schizophrenia now I'm yeah I'm
gonna do that do that read Nick Leon
them get intestinal schizophrenia um
where where are you gonna go that you
weren't gonna go because you thought
something was insane go there you know
like as long as you're treating yourself
well and you're not hurting yourself um
and you're not messing things up you
know like good do what you want with
your brain um so sacrifice so yeah I
think it depends on if it's like a
productive insanity like that um or if
you're actually you like losing you know
like functional parts of you that make
you understand life so to speak I mean
that that's um I don't know if that
would be an act of love it I think it
depends on the individual so yeah as a
follow-up question um so like if you are
in say if you're insane and the right
way and you can seduce everyone else to
your worldview
does that make you insane anymore oh
good question I'm Jesus's father eyes
would say no I I would say no um or at
least seen with Dennis among Korea bum
you have tiny Colts and then you have
small religions and then you have big
religions everything in between you know
if you've got a hoard of father so they
have the same thing that you do at the
very least you're not crazy to them so
you've got like say a hundred people
here you ever seen to you and when when
cults have these you know sanity you
know takeovers I'll call them sanity
take over as per day I'm impose a new
reality into the members brands they
imposed a new reality into the numbers
brands that are in the cold um so they
become seen within that cult I'm
and I can extend some mass religions I'm
but it can also extend to two political
movements where everybody thinks to see
him you know or just like groups of
people who want to enact an agenda yeah
thank you that's good I'd like to move
to Jordan Jordan would you like to meet
yourself and ask a question hey Rachel
I really like what you're talking about
I've been thinking about this issue of
like how whatever is going on right now
we're bumping up into like a real
boundary that just logic and and this
kind of shit is just not capable of
pushing past and so I've been thinking
about this issue of like aesthetic
aesthetic movements that can break
through in the same way and I have a
very hard time thinking of something
that I think would be good except that I
keep realizing and remembering that like
the whole thing with memes is in itself
it seems to fit the it seems to fit the
like the requirement in that it's like
it's a it's like a new form of language
that's primary aesthetic that's one
thing about it it seems to break through
in ways that like other things don't
it's I mean like as a genre of
expression it's like it's a thing from
4chan and like the shit like the other
shit that they do it like doesn't break
through but in but in some other sense
like their whole language of
communication is now how we communicate
on the Internet at least aesthetically
and so there's that little thing but at
the same time it feels like it's not
it's not enough or it's not like it's
like lacking of a kind of vitality I
don't know if you I'm wondering what you
think the limitations are that means
that like even though it seems like from
the description that means qualified but
then like they're not enough yep any
comments on why I think that is yeah
it's a good question I definitely agree
with what you said about the aesthetics
becoming a norm and internet culture and
yeah I mean like not just works you know
but it doesn't mean it's enough right
you you have to
the people who are at least into that is
that like some kind of spark there you
know could that be moves further you
know could could this be something
higher you know and you get a remember
that people grow up with me and this
trio and they might only know me maybe
the only thing they did online and they
might have a really creative mean I mean
sometimes it's just a damn good meeting
and that's why it has so many shares so
you know means they're great no how can
you go beyond that I'm I would say the
forever allowed outside again during
events having salons or philosophy
cabarets is I like to call them that
meetings online you know like we're
doing this saban are gonna be throwing
every other month with musicians and
speakers performance artists and we
might have been humppa fashion show or
two I would encourage everybody to get
involved in these things and get
involved at the Stella and keep coming
to these talks peter has filled I'm
using community here and it's really
just fantastic you seeing so many people
whose ideas I'm interested in speak like
this I mean this is a great way to start
vitality as you say does not exist in
that that culture that's why I think we
need an art culture it does have that
vitality meaning that vitality is an art
culture and maybe they are real just
sort of domesticated because that's like
in line with their agenda and if we have
some day with its more primal and
expressive then we can really change the
architecture of society as it is and
builds new empires of the mind and
reality you know like the
those things something beautiful and
incredible now when do we have that
opportunity in the rubble are we out of
the rubble and retreating a new universe
what will that universe look like what
we have right now what tools will we use
to create these new realities ash would
you like to unmute yourself and ask the
question maybe we will come back to ash
Dominus would you like to make your make
your comment sure so this was a this was
a thought in response to Peters question
to me if we're talking about sanity as
your functional contact with reality
then putting it at risk in order to
explore and expand what reality can mean
for everyone else
through art is absolutely an act of love
as long as you've got people who can
pull you back but I mean love not in a
sense of just affection but I mean it in
the a gothic sense of love where you're
expanding the possibilities of reality
where you're creating an upward spiral
through your creative potential and I
keep thinking of a couple of artists
that I know Jonathan vert and Sasha our
Jones who are actually kind of doing
this in their respective fields with
some very interesting work that goes
against the grain of what you would
expect from their genres oh oh
artist thank you I'm really just happy
to see that some people showed up for
this tag and the statement dresses me
and member Tony's events um me and
Ashley here I believe I'm ribbon he's
here spoke
at 1:00 she gave a talk about tricksters
and archetypes and I would love to have
people collaborate more and find people
in this room like hit me up on Twitter
beyond the center let's work on stuff
that's right let's make music let's go
let's take photography and play with its
design that's odds are let's shift let's
get a motion going
I've creative people working together in
various projects hit up people and tell
them let your visions are and see what
they say chances are you're gonna meet a
lot of like-minded people you know a lot
more people think like you than you
might think
okay that's good for now okay thank you
I have another question about so our
situations communicating through zoom
for example we're now operating so much
more through this like kind of aesthetic
dimension of screens I wonder if you see
a future
transgressive art movement moving beyond
these rectangles interaction I do I
think it's gonna be in virtual reality
but it's gonna take more than virtual
reality to happen it's gonna take people
interacting and a hidings way that they
didn't even it was possible before I
think like in terms of like the hard
future future like we might be so
immersed in this virtual world the laws
of interaction and dynamics they're
gonna completely change and there are so
many possibilities of how we could be
interacting but I don't feel like this
is by any means that we have
I feel like zoom like how we're looking
at it we're gonna look at like Atari
we're gonna look at like zoom like it's
hurry and like 15 maybe 10 here so this
is just a prototype as they say yeah I
was thinking the other day that one day
we'll look back on this with nostalgia
looking at screens because we won't be
doing that anymore
it's aronia days there's gonna be like
thousands of bags can you hop oh go
ahead say no go ahead
I was just gonna ask so from your
experience hosting events in this space
have you seen certain kinds of sparks of
what this like new aesthetic movement
might look like just from exploring this
new territory yeah um he's posting links
on my Twitter with art and fashion I I
used to that Alexander McQueen was a
great example like you look up any of
his videos and you can see like he did
these live fashion shows where he had
the characters interacting like in one
they were playing chess as part of the
fashion show and the pieces were moving
and buying with the runway is really
incredible I'm theater
I mean even even like a more old-school
thing like Lane is their abs if you can
see that and just see how interactive
and how many tents and how primal the
characters are I'm the way they express
themselves um there's something like
like the assassins or Sweeney Todd you
know like that's you that guy is my
favorite Sondheim like if you can get
into Stephen Sondheim you know just just
feel that expression classical music but
try it while you're reading something or
writing something don't just sit there
use the custom of music to drive you if
you can really feel that
you know like those parts of yourself
you know they use that to channel it um
yeah it depends on the person but I
would say don't be afraid to go on the
edge of things you know you couldn't
come back and look somebody said in the
comments um if you have somebody that
can help bring you back you know always
explore don't don't hurt yourself but
always explore if you have the
opportunity it's here you never know
what you might learn and what that might
do for you what do you think about the
the kind of lack of aesthetic expression
that we see in most of the philosophy
community I think that a lot of them
might come from an academic backgrounds
I'm not familiar but by I think maybe
but there's a desire to be seen as
mature and in a way that can be people
the little drab I see that in a lot of
groups and it's just about like building
your own personal elegance and now being
able to create yourself in a way that
you feel it was in line with who you are
I think that in some cultures like some
more Eastern cultures self-expression is
looked down upon for being too
associated with the ego and I I know
like the West is considered over
individualistic so I mean it might
depend on if you're coming at it with a
more like demonic or like a Promethean
energy when I heard Peters talk earlier
I kept thinking of Promethean because he
was talking about stealing on the
culture and thinking about stand the
fire from the gods you know like the
Promethean Renaissance like that's what
those that I've ever met
he's building to atmosphere for me you
know it's the Renaissance
it's the aesthetic Renaissance and
that's what I'm working forward
Raya would you like to admit yourself
and ask a question yes Thank You Raven
and Rachel for being no thank you but
thank you I was just wondering how do we
encourage more people to explore the
nice edge of expression and I said
expression do you mean like the kinds of
hurt I think just like maybe supporting
people and be more being more brave or
courageous and exploring expressive
modalities that they might be curious
about but aren't necessarily like have
the confidence to do it like if they
perceive themselves like oh I can't I'm
a bad singer I'm a bad dancer when in
reality like that doesn't even exist you
know like no one's a bad singer no one's
a bad dancer oh I might disagree with
that life statement but um I think the
people have to get out of those traps
and negative stories about themselves
you know um just if you have negative
stories about yourself that you tell
yourself recognize them you know I'm
like I've been there and I've been like
oh that's that's a negative story I'm
gonna like stop telling myself that
thing um I think a lot of people they're
the reserves because they're afraid of
like shame and we were like shame
culture and like how that could lead to
narcissism I heard this this guy who
gave a talk here um I forget his name
but he was really good he was talking
about how narcissism was based off of
shame and it's interesting how if any
you go dad screws
it's more seams which equals more
narcissism so it's like a perpetual
cycle so you know how helping the avoid
feeling shame to avoid being
narcissistic right um that there's all
sorts of like should you feel shame
shouldn't you and it's really like you
have to answer those questions for
yourself
you know that's not anybody's business
by yours
thank you
yeah it seems like there's this
interesting blending of like so on the
left there's kind of this I don't know
Big Daddy energy where you're like can
somebody do some can someone fix this
problem for me and then the reaction on
the right is like no you have to
bootstrap yourself and I feel like
you're kind of bringing the bringing the
two together like in order to like take
care of everyone we like first must take
care of ourselves and we have to
transgress beyond what has been
considered the acceptable way to express
yeah that's exactly where we are right
now we have an opportunity to explore
taboos and the way that we didn't
previously know existed I think like
what killed chancel culture the
coronavirus because now everybody's
cancelled so everybody can do what they
want now because people don't care about
stupid culture word things because we've
got a freaking bones and I got there oh
my god right so you know I don't even
think those things are relevant anymore
I tend to find mainstream politics to be
very tiring and political consumers to
be even stupider and I would rather
avoid that kind of thing and just focus
on aesthetics I'm divorcing aesthetics
from politics divorcing art from
politics this is where it's really
crucial that if you feel like your art
is making a political steam and that
might be offending a certain group and
you're doing it for that reason are you
really making art or are you just making
politics like to really make art even if
you're inspired by political you know
it's that it's like propaganda or
uniforms or burqa texture whatever it is
you're inspired by politically that you
might not be inspired by politically for
example you guys love those uniforms
right um same kind of being politics are
separate separate but if you feel you
know like your creation is a political
statement you know maybe that's not the
right creation to be having because then
your
not really an artist you're just a
politician who is making art yeah Jordan
had a really good response to this idea
of like you know bad art good art like
what is that dimension Jordan would you
like to make your comment oh I was just
saying that like I think a lot of both
some more underground stuff that I
really appreciate but the when the Joker
movie came out to me it was like a huge
thing because when you look at what is
happening in Hollywood usually you have
these like very very intense aesthetic
things but that they feel very hollow
because they feel like they're made for
a weird like like end in history
ideology kind of that belongs maybe in
like 2005 or something like that and so
they feel hollow despite the fact that
they have all this aesthetic strengths
of them meanwhile now the Joker also has
aesthetic strength but it's calling upon
a lot of ideas that have been
percolating in like online spaces and
shit for a long time and the vitality of
that movie isn't just in the aesthetic
of it although the aesthetics very
important the point the point that I was
making before is that if you're worried
about the fact that maybe you're a bad
artist if the real problem with the art
movement right now is that it's it's not
vital because it's not being honest
about the way shit is and you you don't
really see the world in the way that you
see it in the art right now it's like
there's this weird like vampire not
appearing in the mirror kind of thing so
you could make very compelling art just
by addressing the world as it actually
looks right now even if you're kind of
like a bad rapper or your black
technical skills and so on and that
might be enough to overcome this issue
of like yeah I definitely agree with you
there I mean some people are not gonna
be able to understand you know that kind
of art so to speak but I think
but if you can put it out there and you
should um I think when we're talking
about bad is that like in terms of
aesthetics there's good because there's
some really skilled artists that first
etics but they're just really good the
foundations on and vice versa uh you
know when in the underground scene that
you're talking about you see a lot of
really talented artists that I really
should get the craft but they have
really good ideas and then in the
mainstream you see a lot of people that
are really amazing other problems that
have horrible idea ISM and obviously
what we need is for the people of good
ideas to be working with each other
right on and the people that are good
with their craft to you breaking out
each other um so but what happens the
underground artists to be good enough at
their craft to find somebody that has
more power influence or whatever status
game that can like fine tune them here
yeah you know more more commercial and
acceptable because I mean you you can
like them underground that you not want
people to hear you know I'm that that's
part of like if you've been involved in
like the dark kind of Dawn's things like
goth industrial yada yada um like
there's a lot of stuff that people don't
like that only you and a few people like
you know and then that's okay that's
fine like if you like them like fucked
up films or or whatever it is that
you're into you know I I don't think the
art always needs to be pretty it can be
confrontational and beautiful in a more
aggressive way a more vitalist way that
is a lot heavier where modern art is
we're rightfully complaining up above
before is very light on and submissive
if I hear what you're saying correctly
it doesn't really do anything it doesn't
really move anyone it's not a movement
it's a lack of movement it's a
stagnation I would like to solve stab
you know it would be great to not have
art like that anymore we can't get rid
of it we should create art that isn't
like that offer a better alternative
yeah yeah I think one other thing though
as I mentioned this in another maybe
I'll just throw this in there but I
mentioned this in another thing that we
did there is this guy who has like
almost no followers he used to his like
a punk musician used to call till school
shooter and they had to change his name
to something else because the feds were
coming after him and unlike on Twitter
but he made this really cool song called
MKULTRA victim and it's like really it's
like shittily done because it's like a
guy he's like one guy playing all the
instruments and like the mixing isn't
very good but it's this like really
crazy song about how he's like grown up
with all this like media around him and
and and shit and that it's just like
sucked his soul out of him because now
he has this like like slavish
relationship to to technology and it's
oh it's like really really badass and it
just feels like wow like this this is
something that's alive like in the
moment that we're living in and that
even like the idea is that like the
vitality comes from be like encounter
with the world as it is I like that I
definitely want to check that out that
sometime areas above - really - that on
my I'm thinking about like modern artist
I'm like German Pope is an incredible
artist she does video audio she does
visual art she combines it she's
starting to do it in VR now she has like
she goes by sex death rebirth on Twitter
and her images have a lot of goddess
kind of like a dark goddess kind of
energy like almost like a like a colony
or you know like a different kind of
female like like we were talking about
before you know like the dark someone in
the
you know there's so so much potential
there this is what I see for what could
be a new era you know like we had the
cheerleaders and then we had the jocks
and then we had the Nerds um right and
now we have the the trad Wives right so
what comes after the trad wives all
right what's the next internet
subculture maybe it'll be like the the
Philosopher's Queen's you know like I
think that's what it should be should be
the Philosopher's Queen's that's how we
like super feminism for me insiders in
there yeah and speaking of this
philosopher queen where can people find
you Rachel if they want to get a hold of
you they you can find me on Twitter
beyond the center and I have thing what
I'm gonna be putting up soon I'm but for
now just find me on Twitter and check
out my design agency it's a design dot
live and get ready for an exciting new
launch is coming soon thank you so much
Rachel and also check out her book than
you will all right it's excellent
okay so I am going to tell us about some
upcoming events here at the stoah
tomorrow we have Johannes Neider Howser
coming and he's going to talk to us
about leisure as the basis for the
coming Renaissance it's a similar theme
of aesthetics and that's gonna be at
10:00 a.m. Eastern Time tomorrow then we
have human systems live-action
redesigned with an Lorraine sulk at noon
tomorrow at Eastern Time and another
event later in the afternoon reform of
government institutions namo guru puja
and that's at 4:00 p.m. Eastern Time and
then in the evening we have the
existential dance party date with Colin
Morris of Zion 2.0 podcast so lots of
things going on tomorrow we
to see you join us there if you would
like to RSVP to those events please go
to www.youtube.com and with that thank
you all for being here
Thank You Rachel thank you thanks Rachel
thanks everyone